A Finding Aid to the B. C. Holland Gallery Records, 1942-1991, bulk 1959-1965, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bcholl
Archives of American Art
B. C. Holland Gallery records
bulk 1959-1965
1942-1991
AAA.bcholl
Archives of American Art
2.1 Linear feet
The records of the B. C. Holland Gallery measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1942-1991 (bulk dates 1959-1965). Founded in Chicago, Illinois by Bud C. Holland and Noah Goldowsky, the collection documents over 98 artists associated with the gallery. Documentation includes invoices, correspondence between artists and gallery owners, price lists, exhibition catalogs and print materials, magazine and newspaper clippings, photographs, and slides, and some business records of the gallery.
B.C. Holland Gallery.
Holland, B. C., (Bud C.), 1922-1994
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Artist files, 1942-1991 (2.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, OV 3)
Series 2: Business records, 1961-1963 (1 folder; Box 2)
Biographical/Historical note
B. C. Holland Gallery (1957-1994) was founded by Bud C. Holland and Noah Goldowsky, and was initially known as the Holland-Goldowsky Gallery. It held exhibitions and sold artwork for Chicago artists and many artists of the New York School. Holland bought out his partner and renamed the gallery the B. C. Holland Gallery in August 1961. The gallery closed upon Holland's death in 1994.
Bud C. Holland entered the jewelry business, after serving in WWII as a bomber pilot, where he began collecting artwork. He opened his first art gallery in 1957. During the 1960s pop trend, Holland was drawn towards abstract expressionism and other art forms, which he focused on in his gallery. He began selling his collection when he was diagnosed with cancer, and died at 72 in Chicago, Illinois, 29 December 1994.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the B. C. Holland Gallery measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1942-1991 (bulk dates 1959-1965). Founded in Chicago, Illinois by Bud C. Holland and Noah Goldowsky, the collection documents over 98 artists associated with the gallery. Documentation includes invoices, correspondence between artists and gallery owners, price lists, exhibition catalogues and print materials, magazine and newspaper clippings, photographs, and slides, and some business records of the gallery.
Artists of note include: Harry Bouras, Paul Burlin, Mary Callery, Elaine de Kooning, Willem de Kooning, Jean Dubuffet, Edward Dugmore, Roland Ginzel (including 2 ink drawings), Michael Goldberg, Robert Goodnough, Joseph Goto, Philip Guston, Julius Hatofsky, Richard Hunt (includes 18 files and a landscape plan of John J. Madden Clinic sculpture installation), Lester Johnson, Ellen Lanyon, Alfred Leslie, Jacques Lipchitz, Michael Loew, Knox Martin, Dennis Oppenheim, Stephen Pace, Milton Resnick, Larry Rivers, Aaron Siskind, George Spaventa, Saul Steinberg, Jack Tworkov, and Estaban Vicente.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The B. C. Holland Gallery records were donated to the Archives of American Art by Bud C. Holland's widow, Claire Y. Holland, in 1995.
Bouras, Harry; Burlin, Paul, 1886-1969; Callery, Mary, 1903-1977; De Kooning, Elaine; De Kooning, Willem, 1904-; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-; Dugmore, Edward, 1915-1996; Ginzel, Roland, 1921-; Goldberg, Michael, 1924-; Goldowsky, Noah; Goodnough, Robert, 1917-; Goto, Joseph; Guston, Philip, 1913-1980; Hatofsky, Jerry, 1922-; Holland-Goldowsky Gallery.; Hunt, Richard, 1935-; Johnson, Lester, 1919-; Lanyon, Ellen; Leslie, Alfred, 1927-; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973; Loew, Michael, 1907-1985; Oppenheim, Dennis, 1938-2011; Pace, Stephen, 1918-; Resnick, Milton, 1917-2004; Rivers, Larry, 1925-2002; Siskind, Aaron; Spaventa, George, 1918-; Steinberg, Saul; Tworkov, Jack; Vicente, Esteban, 1903-2001; Art dealers; Art galleries, Commercial--Illinois--Chicago; Art, Modern--20th century--United States; Artists--Illinois--Chicago; Artists--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
- Artist Files, bulk 1959-1965; 1942-1991; Series 1; 2.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are invoices, correspondence between artists and gallery owners, price lists, exhibition catalogues and exhibition print materials, magazine and newspaper clippings, black and white and color photographs, slides, negatives, 2 pieces of artwork, and 1 landscape plan. There are two files containing letters of authenticity and invoices for Gandaharan sculptures, a style of Buddhist art from the Kushan period dating between 1st and 5th centuries A.D., and Haniwa, a style of Japanese sculpture made using the wasumi technique in the Kofun period between 4th and 6th centuries A.D. Correspondence during 1957 and 1961 may include Noah Goldowsky, co-owner of the Holland-Goldowsky Gallery until 1961. Also note that some artist files may contain a single item.
  - Agam, Yaacov, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albers, Josef, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arman, Armand Pierre, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Balthus Klossowski de Rola, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beal, Sondra, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berlant, Anthony, 1962-1964 (Folder 6)
  - Berlet, Marc, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bluhm, Norman, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bouras, Harry, 1959-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Brandt, Warren, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Breland, Bruce, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Burlin, Paul, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Callahan, Harry, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Callery, Mary - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Callery, Mary - Photographs, Catalog, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Caro, Anthony, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Corbett, Ed, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Decker, Lindsey, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - De Kooning, Elaine, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - De Kooning, Willem, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - DeLap, Tony, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dubuffet, Jean, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dugmore, Edward, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Ellsworth, David, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Eversley, Frederick, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gandharan, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ginzel, Roland, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    (Oversized material housed in OV 3)
  - Goldberg, Elias, circa 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Goldberg, Michael, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Goodnough, Robert, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gore, Bert, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Goto, Joseph, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grillo, John, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Guston, Philip, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Haniwa, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hatofsky, Julius, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hedge, Gene, 1961-1991 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Herschler, David, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Howard, Al, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hubbard, Robert, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hunt, Richard - Correspondence, 1961-1983 (Box 1, Folder 49-57)
  - Hunt, Richard - Photographs of Hunt and his artwork, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hunt, Richard - Resumes, Price Lists, circa 1963-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hunt, Richard - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960-1980 (Box 1, Folder 60-61)
  - Hunt, Richard - Clippings, 1961-1979 (Box 1, Folder 62-65)
  - Hunt, Richard - Printed Material, 1961-1982 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Ippolito, Angelo, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Jannes, Georgia, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Johnson, Lester, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 69-72)
  - Kadish, Reuben, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Kerkam, Earl, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Kohn, Gabriel, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Kohn, Misch, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Kostka, Robert, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Kusama, Yayoi, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Kuwayama, Tadaaki, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Lanyon, Ellen, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 80-81)
  - Leslie, Alfred - Correspondence, 1959-1976 (Box 1, Folder 82-84)
  - Leslie, Alfred - Resumes, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Leslie, Alfred - Printed Material, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Levee, John, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Lewis, Golda, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Lince, Richard, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Loew, Michael, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Martin, Knox, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miller, Richard, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mischo, Ivan, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miro, Juan, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell, Joan, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Monaghan, Brian, circa 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Morandi, Giorgio, circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nakian, Reuben, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newbili, Al, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Nickle, Robert, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Oppenheim, Dennis, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Oppenheim, Dennis - Photographs of Artwork, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pace, Stephen, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Pavia, Phillip, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pfriem, Bernard, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Resnick, Milton - Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Resnick, Milton - Correspondence, Biographical Material, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rivers, Larry, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Rocklin, Ray, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rosofsky, Seymour, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Schlemowitz, Abram, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Schueler, Jon, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Seligmann, Kurt, 1942-1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sievan, Maurice - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sievan, Maurice - Photographs of Sievan and his artwork, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Siskind, Aaron, 1959-1989 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
  - Smith, Leon Polk, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Spaventa, George, 1960-1981 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Thompson, Bob, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Tigerman, Stanley, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Travis, Peter, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Tworkov, Jack, 1957-1991 (Box 2, Folder 43-49)
  - Urry, Steven Jay, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Vergette, Nicholas, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Vicente, Estaban, 1959-1991 (Box 2, Folder 52-54)
  - Waite, George, 1961-1986 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Weber, Hugo, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Woelffer, Emerson, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Yampolsky, Phyllis, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Young, David, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 59-60)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - Printed Material, circa 1962-1973 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - A-C, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - D-F, 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - G, 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - H-J, 1959-1976 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - K-L, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - M-N, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - P, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - R-S, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - T-W, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Oversized Ginzel, Roland from Box 1, Folder 34, circa 1966 (Box OV 3)
  - Oversized Hunt, Richard from Box 1, Folder 55, 1963 (Box OV 3)
- Business Records, 1961-1963; Series 2; 1 Folders Box 2
  Found here are a few invoices, correspondence, and notes.
  - Business Records, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 71)